Finding Aid for Michigan Farmers Union records, 1948-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Farmers Union records 1948-2008
Michigan Farmers Union.
2 linear feet
851861 Bg 2
Organization of farmers whose purpose is to promote the welfare and preservation of family farms; minutes, newsletters reports, correspondence, and other organizational records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the MFU came the organization through different members (donor no. 7349 ) beginning in 1986. Earlier smaller accessions were received from Ernie Sawyer (donor no. 4633 ) and Chester Johnson (donor no. 4771 ).
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Farmers Union is an organization of farmers whose purpose is to promote the welfare and preservation of family farms through a program of education, cooperation, and legislation. The Michigan Farmers Union, organized in 1934, is a state organization affiliated with the National Farmers Union. The National Farmers Union was founded in Rains County, Texas, in 1902 as the Farmers Educational and Cooperative Union of America.
The Farmers Union organizational structure is based on individual memberships of farm families. Family memberships cover the parents and all children ages 6-21. The dues-paying member, spouse, and children age 16-21 are eligible to vote in Union matters. Five or more dues-paying members may form a local, which is the basic organizational unit of the Farmers Union. Three or more locals may join to charter a county union. The state Farmers Union is composed of the county and local unions. The National Farmers Union consists of all members of state, county, and local unions.
The first Farmers Union local in Michigan was formed in Hermansville, Menominee County, but there was no systematic organizing effort in the state until the summer of 1933. On July 19, 1933, National Farmers Union President John Simpson spoke to a group of farmers at the Ashland Folk School. The next day, a Farmers Union local was formed at Milan and many others were organized shortly thereafter. The first statewide meeting was held October 10, 1933. The Michigan Farmers Union was chartered and held its first state convention in October 1934. At that time there were more than 300 active locals and over 12,000 members.
In 1936-1937 the Michigan Farmers Union became embroiled in a factional dispute involving both state and national officers. The national office eventually intervened to settle the dispute. Following this episode, membership and organizational activity declined drastically. In the early 1980s, statewide membership totaled approximately 1800.
The Michigan Farmers Union has played an active role in lobbying and educational efforts relating to legislation on agricultural matters at both the state and national levels. It is involved in the operation of a number of agricultural marketing and consumer cooperatives and also provides insurance coverage for members. The Michigan Farmers Union conducts a variety of youth and adult education programs and sponsors projects relating to soil and water conservation and rural development.
The administrative structure of the Michigan Farmers Union consists of a president, two vice presidents, secretary, treasurer, a five-member executive board, and a full board composed of all the county presidents. In recent years the Michigan Farmers Union has maintained an office in Lansing.
The records of the Michigan Farmers Union (MFU) include the MFU constitution and by-laws (rev. 1979, 1993, 2007), minutes, annual reports, policy statements, newsletters, state convention programs and reports, correspondence, material documenting the auxiliary activities of the MFU, biographical material on and photographs of MFU officers, and several printed items on the program and history of the National Farmers Union.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Farm life--Michigan.; Farmers--Michigan.; Grant (Mich.); Newaygo County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Graham, Chester A. (Chester Arthur), 1892-; Michigan Farmers Union.; Farmers' groups.; Cootware, Donna.
Contributors:
Graham, Chester A. (Chester Arthur), 1892-; Johnson, Chester.; Sawyer, Ernie H.; Cootware, Donna.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Organizational materials 1960-2007
  The Organizational materials series includes minutes for the full board of directors, executive board, and annual conventions. The president's annual reports to the state convention review MFU activities for the year. The policy statements detail the official MFU position on agricultural issues and broader social concerns.
  - Constitution and By-laws, revised 1979, 1993, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Board of Directors 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Executive Board 1980, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Annual Conventions 1969, 1977, 1979-1984, 2005 (Box 1)
  - President's Annual Reports 1960-1981 (Box 1)
  - Policy Statements 1964-1985, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- Publicity 1960-1984
  Publicity includes newsletters and press releases, both of which are incomplete.
  - Newsletter
    - 1962, 1966-September 1969 (Box 1)
    - October 1971-October 1976 (Box 1)
    - December 1978-December 1981 (Box 1)
    - January 1982-1992 1995 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1980-1984 (Box 1)
- State Conventions 1948-1984
  State conventions programs are printed booklets listing the convention agenda, state officers, and state committee members. The state convention reports may include reports from state officers and various committees and financial statements. None of these files are complete, even for the years listed.
  - Programs 1948-2008, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 1980-1984, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1962-1984
  The correspondence deals primarily with convention and meeting plans, with only occasional items relating to MFU programs and policies.
  - 1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981 (Box 2)
  - 1982 (Box 2)
  - January-September 1983 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - Vice-President's Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    (drafts of outgoing letters)
- Project files 1979-1985
  The material on auxiliary MFU activities includes limited amounts of correspondence, reports, and press releases on the following projects that MFU sponsored or participated in: American Farm Project (1980), Depression in Rural America (1982), Family Farm Preservation Campaign (1979-1982), Family Farm Crisis Day (1982), Farm Organization Summit Meeting (1982-1983), Green Thumb Project (1982-1984), and the Soil and Water Conservation Awards (1983-1985).
  - The American Farm Project 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Depression in Rural America 1982 (Box 2)
  - Family Farm Preservation Campaign 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Farm Crisis Day 1982 (Box 2)
  - Farm Organization Summit Meeting 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Green Thumb Project 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - National Soil and Water Conservation Awards 1983-1985, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Other papers
  The Other papers series includes lists of new members and membership renewals for 1980. Unfortunately, these do not constitute a complete roster of members. There is also some biographical information about Chester A. Graham and other officers, some photographs, and printed material. There are also some records for the Newaygo County and Grant, Michigan chapters.
  - Biographical Material
    - State Officers (Box 2)
    - Chester A. Graham (includes some of Graham's writings) (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists 1980 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, Affidavits and, Speeches 1961-1983 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Printed Material (Box 2)
  - Grant Farmers Union record book 1956-1965 include minutes and financial and membership information (Box 2)
  - Newaygo County Farmers Union record books 1962-1978 minutes and financial membership information (Box 2)
Related Material
Additional material on the Michigan Farmers Union, especially for the early years of the organization, can be found in the Chester Arthur Graham papers.